<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rector of Bury's reply to the minister at Oswestry's answer; in a second letter to his friend</title>
            <author>Gipps, Thomas, d. 1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42784</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G779B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213346</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825761</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825761</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30148</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42784)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30148)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1793:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rector of Bury's reply to the minister at Oswestry's answer; in a second letter to his friend</title>
                  <author>Gipps, Thomas, d. 1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Gipps.</note>
                  <note>Caption title; imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to Owen, James.  A further vindication of the dissenters from the Rector of Bury's unjust accusations.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Owen, James, 1654-1706 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:30148:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30148:1"/>
            <head>THE
Rector of Bury's Reply
TO THE
Miniſter at Oſweſtry's Anſwer;
In a Second Letter to his Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Was in hopes my former Letter might have Charm'd
the good Man, and laid that evil Spirit which Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
him. But I am miſtaken: Mr. <hi>O.</hi> is no Change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
he chuſeth ſtill to Scrible for the <hi>Diverſion</hi> rather
than the <hi>Edification</hi> of his Reader, as himſelf I am told has
confeſs'd, and which is manifeſt in the <hi>Anſwer.</hi> It is leſs to
be wonder'd at, ſeeing this Itch of Writing ſcurrilouſly
ſeems to run in the Blood, as you rightly obſerv'd from
<hi>Eugenius</hi> his late Pamphlet. With much ado he has pickt
up Four Inſtances out of my <hi>Letter,</hi> and by the help of
miſrepreſentation, would Skreen himſelf from the Cenſure
of Wiſe Men, as if he had only beaten the Rector at his
own Weapon. Much good may his Victory do him. I am
not, I own, skill'd in that Noble Science of Fencing with
an Adverſary, and inſtead of Anſwering his Arguments,
abuſing him with Contemptuous Language.</p>
            <p>He informs you,<note n="*" place="margin">Title Page.</note> 
               <hi>The Rector has effectually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted
the Diſſenters,</hi> &amp;c. And this I'll warrant you muſt
paſs for Truth, without looking into the <hi>Letter</hi> or the <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
Oh, ſay the Mob, its a plain caſe, our Oracle has ſaid it, the
Rector is baffl'd even by his own Confeſſion; whilſt the
more underſtanding ſort droop, hang the Head, and are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30148:2"/>
aſham'd of their Advocate. But how doth he prove this?
Why, he ſums up the cauſe, (you may be ſure partially
enough) he tells, what feats he has done, what Havock he
has made in the Rector's Squadrons <hi>(i. e.</hi> Arguments,)
the moſt part whereof he has diſmounted, trampl'd under
foot, left ſprawling on the ground, and weltring in their
Bloud, whilſt the reſt being put into diſorder were forc'd
to fly and retire with Precipitation; the unhappy General
mean while being unable to rally or recruit his broken
Forces.</p>
            <p>Now the pretence for all this boaſting is, The Rector not
diſtruſting the Judgment of the Intelligent Reader, would
not trouble him with impertinent Repetitions: But left his
Squadrons in the Field firm, and in good order, as they
were, and (he believ'd) able to make good their Ground
againſt all Oppoſition. There was then no neceſſity of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing
his Troops, which had ſuſtain'd no conſiderable
loſs, that he knows of, nor is he yet ſenſible there is need
of any new Levies. By this time the Metaphor is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
ſqueez'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Titles are left out of the Liturgy Pſalms, becauſe intended
to be Sung.</hi> This in good time is agreed upon as a juſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But Mr. <hi>O.</hi> will needs
have the Honour of firſt ſtarting it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> p. 14.</note> 'Tis not
worth while to ask why Mr. <hi>Delaune</hi>'s Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
ſhould deſert and turn on the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s ſide.
This is no good ſign of Victory. Nor is it <hi>tanti,</hi> which of
us can lay the beſt claim to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch as it is. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they ſay, there is as much right in a Penny as in a
Pound, I'll not loſe it for lack of demanding. See then <hi>Rs.
Rs.</hi> p. 15. l. 34. which were written before Mr. <hi>O</hi>'s <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
So that <hi>Mr.</hi> Miniſter is <hi>beholden</hi> to <hi>Mr.</hi> Rector for
that <hi>Plea,</hi> if a trifling Truth may be ſpoken. <hi>Hos ego ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiculos
feci, tulit alter Honorem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pretend not to a Preſident in Antiquity, or a Rubrick
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30148:2"/>
in our Church for repeating the <hi>Pſalms</hi> alternately<note n="*" place="margin">Yet ſee Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks before Hymns of 5th <hi>Nov. 30 Jan. 29 May,</hi> and Fire of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </note>.
But I reckon Cuſtom a good warrant for it, which
as 'tis eſteem'd a ſecond Nature in one caſe, ſo in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
is to be accounted a ſecond ſort of Command<note n="†" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 16.</note>.
We cannot tranſgreſs it without being Schiſmaticks.
<hi>Saying</hi> the <hi>Pſalms</hi> is a kind of Singing them, being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd
from reading them by way of Inſtruction: For they
are appointed, as part of our Devotion, which the Cuſtom of
our Church has determin'd unto alternate ſaying. We have
no other Order for Singing the <hi>Pſalms</hi> in Meter, but Cuſtom.</p>
            <p>That Women may ſpeak in the Church is doubtleſs true,
<hi>1 Cor.</hi> 11. 5. where by <hi>Propheſying</hi> I underſtand
<hi>Singing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 25, 1, 2, 3, 6, 7.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi> indeed forbids them to ſpeak
in the Church, <hi>1 Cor.</hi> 14. 34, 35. but explains
himſelf, <hi>1 Tim.</hi> 2. 12. That they are not to Teach, or Speak
Authoritatively: However they may ſpeak in Prayer and
Praiſe. Is it not lawful for 'em to ſay <hi>Amen?</hi> Do not the
Diſſenters allow them to Sing? In a word, when prejudices
are laid aſide, <hi>Noiſe and Confuſion</hi> may be objected againſt
<hi>Singing</hi> as reaſonably, as againſt <hi>ſaying</hi> the <hi>Pſalms alternatìm.</hi>
The Quakers will deride the Diſſenters Singing <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Pſalms,</hi>
and call it <hi>Gibble Gabble,</hi> or <hi>bouncing and racketing</hi> them (in
<hi>Eugenius</hi> his Language) with as much Reaſon and Juſtice, as
the Diſſenters can our ſaying them alternately.</p>
            <p>I will be better than my word, and let Mr. <hi>O.</hi> ſee, I am able
to recruit my Squadrons, though he has not ſhatter'd or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd
them: that the Titles of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> are not Eſſential
Parts of them, ſeems to be the Opinion of Mr. <hi>Allix,</hi>
who Writes,<note place="margin">Judgment of the Jewiſh Church, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <q>It is by the help of Tradition, that
the Ancient Interpreters have added to the <hi>Pſalms</hi>
ſuch Titles, as expreſs their Deſign and their U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
in the Synagogue.</q> One might hope to find
ſhelter under the Wings of this Learned Perſon, at leaſt to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted
of Blaſphemy, if not of all Error or miſtake.</p>
            <p>I refus'd the Arbitration of <hi>Jerom,</hi> for Reaſons, which were
not to the Honour of that Father. On th' other Hand, Mr. <hi>O.</hi>
has adorn'd him with wonderful Encomiums in general. But
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30148:3"/>
               <hi>quid verba audio, cum facta video.</hi> If all were true, his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
Faults are not covered thereby. The Rector was forc'd to
Treat him in that manner to ſatisfy the Reader why he declin'd
<hi>his</hi> Judgment, who was too Sceptical in the point to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded.
But Mr. <hi>Br.</hi> without neceſſity let fly, and at once
mauld and put to the Sword the whole Squadron of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>B.</hi> 4th p. 1025.</note> Nor do I want a very good Preſident for what
I did, the Famous Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <q>St. <hi>Jerom</hi> (ſaith
he) is a Man of no Faith with me, when he deſcribes the
Opinion of his Adverſary, which he would ſet forth as odiouſly
as poſſibly could be. He was a Man that car'd not what he
ſaid,<note place="margin">Id. B. 3. p. 748.</note> ſo it might diſparage his Adverſaries, as in
the caſe of <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> and <hi>Jovinian; Again,</hi> St.
<hi>Jerom</hi> was a moſt unequal Relator of the Opinion of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary.
What Credit he may deſerve in this may appear in
ſome fragments of thoſe Authors ſtill remaining, whom he
charg'd with an Opinion directly contrary to that which they
expreſly affirm'd. And yet when he had ſtated it ſo, as it
muſt needs be Hereſy and Blaſphemy whoſoever held it, he
is found to ſay he durſt not damn it, becauſe <hi>Multi virorum
Eccleſiaſticorum &amp; Martyrum iſta dixerunt.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Sic oculos, ſic ille manus, ſic or a—: <hi>unriddle me this,</hi> &amp; Phyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lida
ſolus habeto.</p>
            <p>That all Ancient verſions of Scripture and the Fathers are
uſeful to find the true Reading of Scripture will eaſily be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
if you call to Mind what account we all make of the Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glot
Bibles and Primitive Writers. That a Verſion of leſs
Credit in general may in ſome particulars be truer than even
the LXX. or the Hebrew ſeems to be the Opinion
of Mr. <hi>Mede.</hi>
               <note place="margin">B. 5. p. 1095, 1096.</note> He obſerv'd, that in both the Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology
of <hi>Gen. 11. 26, 32. ch.</hi> 12. 4. compar'd
with <hi>Lu.</hi> 7. 4. was miſtaken, and Corrected it by the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
Pentateuch.</hi> Now though for my own part I believe the
Hebrew and LXX are not here faulty for Reaſons not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
to be adduc'd in this place, yet this ſhews what that good
Man's Sentiments were in the Caſe. Of the ſame mind is the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30148:3"/>
Learned <hi>Dupin.</hi> 
               <q>'Tis not abſolutely neceſſary
(ſaith he) that we ſhould always follow the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan
Pentateuch (which he aſſerts to be an Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
and Authentick)</hi> nor are we always oblig'd to
follow the Hebrew Text.</q>
               <note place="margin">Compleat Hiſt. of the <hi>O.</hi> and <hi>N.</hi> Teſtam. Part 1. p. 168.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>O.</hi> is angry, that (as the Papiſts ſend us to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
for the ſenſe of Scripture ſo) the Rector carries us to them
for the Scripture it ſelf. Bleſs me, thought I when I read this,
whither will vain Glory and thirſt after Victory drive a Man,
and into what Abſurdities betray him? This <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
is very fatal. Becauſe, forſooth, we ought not without fear
or wit depend on the Fathers <hi>only</hi> for the ſenſe of Scripture,
neither are we beholden to them for the Scripture it ſelf.
Whence (I beſeech you) had we the Scripture, but from our
Predeceſſors in the Faith? The Holy Fathers Principally,
whoſe Writings are ſo many everlaſting Monuments upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord
of their Divine Authority from whom we know, what
Books were and what were not written by Inſpiration.
Whence did we derive this knowledge but from them? It was
not brought us by an Angel from Heaven: We have it not by
Inſpiration, or from an inſpir'd Prophet: It dropt not out of
the Clouds, neither were we born with an innate Idea, or No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Divine Scriptures, which are and which are not ſuch.</p>
            <p>If the examples already produced do not prove Corruptions
in the Hebrew Text (I am ſure as zealous ſticklers for the
Hebrew verity as Mr. <hi>O.</hi> can be,<note place="margin">Mede b. 4. p. 961, 990, b. 3. 707, 708. 709. b. 5. 1094.</note> have confeſſed it)
I ſend you then to the Margin for more. In one
of theſe places our Author Writes to A. B. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>
thus, <q>I durſt ſhew no ſuch Conceits as theſe,
but to ſo great an Antiquary, to whom the poſſibility of
Corruption by Writing is ſo well known, or rather the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility
to the contrary. How can it be prov'd, that
the Church of the Jews had a greater Privilege than
we, eſpecially ſince Propheſy ceaſed among them? The
Maſorethical method was deviſed ſince Chriſt and applied to
one Copy only, the beſt, written by <hi>Hillel:</hi> Suppoſing this,
yet other Copies might in ſome things be righter than <hi>Hill<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s.</hi>
               </q>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:30148:4"/>
He argues elſe where, the Hebrew is moſt liable to Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
the Letters differing ſo very little are eaſily miſtaken one for
another. There is no ſecurity againſt Corruption, unleſs the
Tranſcribers were inſpir'd: But whether for theſe Nineteen
Hundred Years paſt any one Copier has been inſpir'd, who he was,
and which is the Copy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ib.</hi> p. 961.</note> and where to be ſeen tell, me,
<hi>&amp; eris mihi magnus Apollo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any Corruption</hi> ('tis pleaded) <hi>had crept into the Text, the Pen
Men of the</hi> N. T. <hi>would have Corrected it. And what if they did?
But we had rather follow the</hi> Maſorites, ſaith Mr. <hi>M.</hi> He after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
obſerves ſeveral ſuch Emendations, which you may
examine at leiſure. Is it not then equally probable, that St. <hi>Paul</hi>
in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> reſtor'd the 13, 14, 15, 16, 17,
and 18. Verſes, to the 14th <hi>Pſalm?</hi> But we dote on the <hi>Maſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,</hi>
and had rather ſtoop to the <hi>Rabbins</hi> than to the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Juſtin</hi> underſtood the Hebrew, ſo I argu'd from his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
a Native of <hi>Flavia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apol. 2. in init.</note> a City in <hi>Paleſtine.</hi> This
Squadron Mr. <hi>O.</hi> meddles not with: It keeps the Field ſtill as I
might ſay peacebly. But (ſaith he) the Martyr has miſtaken
the Etymology of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> For it is deriv'd from <hi>Sarah; Iſh</hi> (not
<hi>Is)</hi> ſignifies <hi>vir,</hi> and therefore he will not allow <hi>Juſtin</hi> to have
been skill'd in Hebrew. <hi>A.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Criticks take a great deal of Liberty in Etymologies, they
are like Hereticks in Religion, often broaching new Conceits,
which though not always exactly true are not to be aſcrib'd
unto their Ignorance, but ſingularity and a certain Delight
they take <hi>ludere Campo Philologiae,</hi> and to ſtart Paradoxes in that
kind of Learning, ſuiting their Etymologies to the Argument
before them. The Martyr doubtleſs had his Eye upon <hi>Gen.
32.</hi> 24. where the Perſon that Wreſtled with <hi>Jacob</hi> is call'd
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>vir</hi> from whence he fancy'd <hi>Iſrael</hi> was deriv'd. For
the Eternal <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here appearing in the ſhape of a Man, and
being therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> gave unto <hi>Jacob</hi> his own Name (as
I ſhall ſhew) a name ſuitable to his own Nature, and Typical
of it. <hi>Juſtin</hi>'s Criticiſm therefore is not contemptible, nor is he
to be thought a dunce in the Hebrew on this ſcore. But you'll
ask perhaps, why then did not <hi>Juſtin</hi> write <hi>Iſh?</hi> And how comes
it to paſs that we write it <hi>not Iſhrael,</hi> but <hi>Iſrael? A.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:30148:4"/>
2. As for <hi>Juſtin</hi> you muſt note the Greeks have no ſuch
Letter as <hi>ſh</hi> which therefore they always turn into a ſimple
<hi>s,</hi> as may be ſeen in the LXX. and Greek Teſtament: <hi>Ex.
Gr. Shimeon</hi> in the Hebrew, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29. 33. is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the LXX.
and in <hi>Lu.</hi> 2. 25. and <hi>Shem, Gen.</hi> 5. 33. is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the LXX. and in
<hi>Lu.</hi> 3. 36. So that we need not wonder <hi>Juſtin</hi> Martyr Writes <hi>Is</hi>
for <hi>vir,</hi> tho' the Hebrew writes it <hi>Iſh.</hi> And as for us in Engliſh,
we very frequently turn <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> into <hi>Sin,</hi> as if there were no difference
between the two Letters. We Write <hi>Simeon, Iſaiah, Samuel,
Abſolom, Ahaſuerus,</hi> and others, with a <hi>Sin</hi> in ſtead of the <hi>Shin,</hi>
from whence I infer that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was Originally but one Letter, tho'
afterwards made two, and deſtinguiſh'd by a point on the right
Shoulder of <hi>Shin,</hi> and on the left of <hi>Sin. Buxtorf</hi> thinks that
<hi>Shin</hi> was the only Ancient Letter of the Hebrew Alphabet, <hi>Sin</hi>
being brought into the Room of <hi>Samech,</hi> haply after <hi>Juſtin</hi>'s
time. If ſo then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the ſame Letter in <hi>Iſrael</hi> and in <hi>Iſh.</hi> Note
again, that the Ephraimites, <hi>Jud.</hi> 12. 6. could not pronounce
<hi>Shin,</hi> but ſaid <hi>Sibboleth</hi> inſtead of <hi>Shibboleth:</hi> Queſtionleſs then
they ſaid <hi>Is</hi> alſo and not <hi>Iſh,</hi> and ſo with them there was no ſuch
Letter as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> nor any uſe of it: 'Tis probable it might be thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<hi>Flavia,</hi> which haply occaſion'd <hi>Juſtin</hi>'s Etymology. In
this variety and uncertainty about the Letter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 'tis hard <hi>Juſtin</hi>
ſhould be taxt for want of skill in the Hebrew Tongue, tho'
he took the Liberty of Starting an uncommon Etymology:
But eſpecially conſidering it was offer'd in confirmation of the
human Nature of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Trypho</hi> the Jew had nothing to
object againſt it, one would be apt to believe it was the true
one. But,</p>
            <p>3. Upon a review of that Paſſage in <hi>Juſtin</hi> Martyr, 'tis very
probable the Father hit upon the true Etymology of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which
he tells us ſignifies <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Iſ-ra-el</hi> by Contraction. 'Tis true preſently after he renders
<hi>Iſra</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> leaving out <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but it may well be imagin'd a
defect or fault of the <hi>M. S.</hi> ſeeing he had before obſerv'd, that
<hi>Iſrael</hi> ſignifyed a <hi>Man overcoming God.</hi> At leaſt (I hope) <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>t
will not be deny'd but that there is a great deal of ingenuity in
<hi>Juſtin</hi>'s Criticiſms, and that 'tis likely enough he underſtood
the Hebrew Language.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:30148:5"/>
4. Granting <hi>Juſtin</hi> has given us a wrong Etymology of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
it will not follow he underſtood not Hebrew. One might by
the ſame Reaſon affirm Mr. <hi>O.</hi> underſtands neither Greek nor
Latin, nor yet Engliſh, but Welſh only, becauſe he has mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken
himſelf ſometime or other in all thoſe Languages. But
this is manifeſt, the Martyr frequently quotes the Hebrew as
well as the LXX. where there was a different Reading, <hi>Dial. p.
360.</hi> and gives us the Reaſon of it, <hi>viz. That his Reaſoning
thence might not be ſet at naught by the Jews,</hi> that various Reading
being not concerned in his preſent Argument with <hi>Trypho.</hi> By
the way then I infer hence, as very probable, that <hi>Juſtin</hi> us'd the
ſame Care and precaution, when he Challeng'd the Jews with
corrupting the Scriptures, that is, had his Eye upon both Texts.</p>
            <p>But I am ſurpriz'd that Mr. <hi>O.</hi> ſhould aſſert, that in the
Word <hi>Iſrael, by</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>El Juſtin means no other God, but the
God of this World the Devil, which the blund'ring Rector</hi> (elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where
call'd blind <hi>Bayard) makes to ſignify the true God.</hi> Is the
Man poſſeſt? What? The true God gave the name of the Devil
unto the Holy Patriarch, and that becauſe he Wreſtl'd with the
true God and prevail'd? It could never enter into any
good Man's Noddle that the Divine <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bleſſed Jacob</hi>
with the Devil's name, I will at Adventures affirm the Martyr
never thought nor ſaid ſo. A little after indeed he uſeth <hi>El</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for the <hi>Devil,</hi> whom he deſcribes for diſtinction ſake, <hi>the
Serpent and Satan,</hi> but not with reference unto <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
In ſhort,<note place="margin">Juſt. Dial. p. 355. E. P.</note> he hath by good luck clear'd himſelf, in
this matter thus, <hi>Iſrael was his name from above</hi>
(<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from Heaven) <hi>by which Chriſt call'd Jacob Bleſſing him
with his own name,</hi> but not with the Devil's ſurely.</p>
            <p>I am ſtill of the mind, that with <hi>Jerom</hi> and in his time the
Hebrew read <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 8. as the LXX. doth at this day. All
Nations but <hi>Iſrael</hi> were ſubjected to the Angels, and govern'd
by them as the Learned believe, which Dr. <hi>Scot</hi>
has well explain'd and confirm'd.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſtian Life</hi> Par. 2. p. 935. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> He farther
ſhews how probably <hi>Angels</hi> in that Text was chang'd
into <hi>Children of Iſrael.</hi> Originally it ran thus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Sons of God,</hi> q. d. <hi>Angels,</hi> but the Tranſcribers ſuſpecting <hi>Iſra</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:30148:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to be left out reſtor'd it, and ſo it became <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> q. d.
<hi>Children of Iſrael.</hi> Setting this aſide, <hi>Jerom</hi> holding the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
of Angelocracy confirm'd from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 8. according to
the LXX. ſaith Mr. <hi>O.</hi> But this he would never have done contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
to the Hebrew verity, preferring the LXX. to it. His good
Friends and Allies the Jews, would con him no thanks for this,
as I gueſs.</p>
            <p>There is a perfect Agreement (Mr. <hi>O.</hi> avers it) between the
Hebrews and the LXX. in <hi>1 Sam.</hi> 17. he knows it to be ſo,
he has <hi>conſulted</hi> the Chapter, and you may depend upon it.
But blind <hi>Bayard</hi>'s Eyes once more deceive him, or Mr. <hi>O.</hi> is
taken in the manner once more. What will not ſome Men ſay
to ſave their Bacon? Twenty Four Verſes of that 17th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> are miſſing in the LXX. a<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that there is a
perfect Agreement between them. Mr. <hi>O.</hi> might as well
acquaint the World that he and I are agreed <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Beſides, let
him compare the 16, 17, and 18th Chapters, as I deſir'd him,
and then tell me, if the LXX. have not given us a ſtraight
and intelligible Narrative of <hi>David</hi>'s Action, whilſt in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
the courſe of the ſtory is intolerably broken, perplext and
tranſpos'd without remedy. Mr. <hi>O.</hi> ſees nothing of this, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
I know a Child of twelve Years Old, who t'other day
diſcerning the diſorder, ask'd whether there were
two <hi>Davids,</hi> one <hi>Saul</hi>'s Armour bearer<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 16.</note>, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
that ſlew <hi>Goliah</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Chap. 17.</note>, becauſe <hi>Saul</hi> knew him
not, <hi>v.</hi> 55.</p>
            <p>I am content Mr. <hi>O.</hi> ſhould have the Liberty of explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
himſelf, when he ſaith, <hi>The not reading the Titles of the</hi>
Pſalms <hi>is an innocent Omiſſion;</hi> which (he pleads) was ſpoken
in excuſe of the Parochial Aſſemblies, and not of the Diſſenters
(as the Rector miſtakes) <hi>they do read the Titles.</hi> But
the matter is not yet mended: His words are<note n="*" place="margin">Farther Vind. <hi>p.</hi> 53.</note>,
<q>Now ſince the <hi>Pſalms</hi> are read not ſung
in our Parochial Churches, the Titles which are Part of the
Scripture ought not to be expung'd out of the Reading
<hi>Pſalter</hi>—They may and <hi>ought</hi> to be read as part of the Word
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30148:6"/>
of God and therefore ſhould not be left out of the Reading
<hi>Pſalms.</hi> But this is not the Controverſy between me and the
Rector:</q> The not reading of them is an innocent Omiſſion.
In ſhort thus, the Titles <hi>ought</hi> to be read in Parochial Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies
becauſe the <hi>Pſalms</hi> are read there and not ſung, but yet
the not reading them is an <hi>innocent</hi> Omiſſion. Is not this rare
ſtuff? That any thing which <hi>ought</hi> to be done can be <hi>innocently</hi>
left undone, to ſpeak ſoftly, is a ſtrange Paradox beyond my
reach to comprehend. I'll not call it <hi>vile, impious and profane:</hi>
But I cannot Swallow it. At this Rate we may e'en fling a
way our Bibles, renounce all Religion and Morality. As for
the Diſſenters reading the Titles, I would ask how often, and
by what Orders. There is no direction for it in the <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Liturgy</hi> where one ought to expect it. Beſides, I
have been frequently at Presbyterian Aſſemblies, where not ſo
much as the <hi>Pſalms</hi> themſelves were read, and near a thouſand
times (I believe) where, though the <hi>Pſalms</hi> were now and
then read, yet the Titles were not. Innocent Omiſſion! In
ſhort the Diſſenters, if one may gueſs at their Principles by
their Practice, do not take themſelves abſolutely oblig'd to read
the Scripture in their ſtated Aſſemblies, but will omit this Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony
when ever they pleaſe to make room for their own
Sermons and Lecturings, which juſtle out the Word of God.
And the People Love to have it ſo: They complain not, if
Reading the Word be paſs'd by and neglected: But if there
be no Sermon, what outcries will they make, as if they were
ſtarv'd for lack of Bread? And again, when the Word of God
is read, they ſit like ſo many dull and lifeleſs Images till the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
begins his Harangue: Then they rouſe, and liſten with
wonderful attention, ſeeming to be unwilling one Word of his
Mouth ſhou'd drop by the way unobſerv'd. Now is it fit
theſe Men ſhould reproach us for reading the Apocrypha now
and then, or omitting the Titles of the <hi>Pſalms?</hi> It were to be
wiſh'd Men would ſee their own Faults and amend them in
ſtead of quarrelling at our innocent Omiſſions and Appointments.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30148:6"/>
As to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s and the <hi>Homily</hi>'s leaving out <hi>Theſe</hi> in their
citation of <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 28, and (as Mr. <hi>O.</hi> argues) their being
equally concern'd in the Accuſation, ſo that either both are, or
neither of them ought to be acquitted, I will now in the laſt
place ſhew the contrary, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s buſineſs in the <hi>Petition for Peace</hi> was in general
to prove the unlawfulneſs of impoſing any but neceſſary things
in Religious Worſhip, which he pretended to make good from
<hi>Act.</hi> 15. 28. quoting it thus—<hi>It ſeemed good to the Apoſtles and Elders
to lay upon them no greater burden than neceſſary things,</hi> and omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>Theſe.</hi> Now this Word had it not been ſuppreſs'd would
have put the Reader upon recollecting or ſearching what thoſe
neceſſary things were in particular; indeed it would have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd
Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himſelf in Reaſon to have mention'd them all.
But that would have quite ſpoil'd his Argument. For every
one then would have perceiv'd at firſt ſight, that the Text
ſpeaks only of matters belonging to civil Converſation. But
expreſſing the Paſſage thus, <hi>neceſſary things</hi> indefinitely, the
Reader would be apt to run away with the Bait, and take it
for granted, that the Apoſtles appointed nothing in Religious
Worſhip, but neceſſary things, which is not nor can be prov'd
from this Text. In ſhort, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Argument (which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
is none at all) appear'd plauſible by the Omiſſion of <hi>Theſe,</hi>
and he is juſtly ſuſpected to have deſign'd to inſnare his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.
I know an ingenious Perſon who was thus deceiv'd by
him.</p>
            <p>But the Author of the <hi>Homilie</hi> cannot juſtly be tax'd with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
ſuch fallacious Deſign. He was urging the particular Duty
of abſtaining from Fornication as neceſſary, and prov'd it from
the Text, which <hi>among other</hi> neceſſary things forbids Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
His Argument is neither better nor worſe by his omitting
<hi>Theſe.</hi> Nay, the Turn of the whole Period, as he contriv'd
it, would not admit <hi>Theſe</hi> to be taken in. It would have been
Non-ſenſe to ſay—<hi>Theſe neceſſary things: Among others they willed
them:</hi> This latter Word <hi>Other</hi> in a New diſtinct Sentence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd,
that <hi>Theſe</hi> ſhould be left out in the former. But enough
and too much of this trivial Point.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:30148:7"/>
Here then I put an end unto my Notes on Mr. <hi>Owens</hi>'s <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
If you or any Body elſe ſhould think it worth while ſtrictly
to examine all that has paſs'd between him and me
throughout this whole Controverſy, I again declare I muſt
ſend you to our former Writings, being loath to give you or
my ſelf any unneceſſary Trouble. And I am pretty well aſſur'd
the generality of Readers would not like being teaz'd with
the Repetition of the ſame things over again: I am ſenſible
it would be to very little purpoſe. I remain then,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Affect. and very
Humble Servant.
<hi>T. G.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:30148:7"/>
            <head>THE
PUBLISHER
TO THE
READER.</head>
            <p>EVery Body almoſt has taken notice of the ſtrange Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
that is in the <hi>1 Sam.</hi> 16, 17, 18, Chapters.
There came to my hands very lately the following Eſſay,
which pretends to reſtore them to their Natural Order,
and gives a Conjecture how poſſibly this Confuſion might
have happen'd. In the Abſence of the Author of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going
Letter, there being ſo near an Agreement in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,
I have made bold to add this as an Appendix, the
rather becauſe the ſaid Author ſeems to believe, the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties,
wherewith theſe Chapters are perplext, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperable
and without Remedy.</p>
            <p>That the Courſe of the Hiſtory of <hi>David,</hi> in <hi>1 Sam. 16, 17,
18,</hi> Chapters is diſorder'd, every one ſees, and the <hi>Septuagint</hi>
for that Reaſon (as I fanſie) in their Verſion, or ſome Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriber,
has intirely expung'd Twenty four Verſes out of
the 17. Chapter, and Eight out of the 18. by which means
they made the ſtory very eaſy and intelligible, and diſcharg'd
it of all the difficulties, which appear in our Bibles at this
Day. But 'tis very hard me thinks to imagine how Four and
twenty, and Eight Verſes, could have been interpolated in
the ſacred Text, ſeeing they contain a piece of the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
which no where elſe is ſo much as hinted at. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
chuſe of the two, to believe rather that the parts of the
Narrative have been tranſpos'd, which therefore I am
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30148:8"/>
endeavouring to reſtore unto their right Order. But firſt
let us take a view of the Diſorders in theſe three Chapters,
as we now have them in the Hebrew Text and our Engliſh
Verſion.</p>
            <p>1. In the 17th Chapter we have an Account of <hi>David</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily
and Pedegree, which is to be found immediately before
in the 16th Chapter, and without any neceſſity repeated
here. Whereas on the contrary, if we invert the Order of
theſe two Chapters, the Repetition of them is neceſſary,
as any one that conſiders will confeſs.</p>
            <p>2. In the 17th Chapter <hi>David</hi> is employ'd in the meaneſt
Offices by his Father <hi>Jeſſe, viz.</hi> tending the Sheep; and
Snub'd by his Eldeſt Brother <hi>Eliab,</hi> as too Ambitious and
Aſpiring, though Chapter 16. he had been in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
of his Father and Brethren Anointed <hi>Saul</hi>'s Succeſſor,
and the deſign'd King of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Neither of which I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded
ought nor would have been done after <hi>David</hi>'s
Anointing.</p>
            <p>3. In Chapter 17. <hi>Saul</hi> calls <hi>David</hi> Youth, unfit to enter
the Liſts with the Giant, not knowing what it was to Fight;
and eſpecially 'tis obſervable, that the King again after the
Fight, calls him Young Man and Stripling, tho' Chapter 16.
<hi>David</hi> had ſometime before been Anointed King, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd
to be <hi>Saul</hi>'s Armour-Bearer, and was then known
to be a <hi>Man of War, and prudent in Matters.</hi> All which
ſuppoſe that he was beyond a Stripling, in the 16th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and much more in the 17th.</p>
            <p>4. In the 17th Chapter <hi>Saul</hi> ſeems not to have known
<hi>David</hi>'s Pedegree and Family, and therefore enquires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
it: Probably he knew not his Name, for he never calls
him <hi>David,</hi> but only Youth, Stripling and Young Man.
Whereas all this was well known unto <hi>Saul</hi> before, Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
16.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:30148:8"/>
5. In the 18th Chapter, the 6, 7, &amp; 8. Verſes are manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
broken off from the 17th Chapter, which they ought
immediately to follow, but are interrupted with Five
Verſ<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, the laſt whereof acquaints us, that <hi>Saul</hi> employ'd
<hi>David</hi> in buſineſs of Importance, ſet him over the Men of
War: That <hi>David</hi> behav'd himſelf Wiſely, and got the
Favour of the People and of the Courtiers, which muſt
needs have happen'd after <hi>Saul</hi>'s Triumphant Return from
the ſlaughter of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> which nevertheleſs we ſee
is poſtpon'd to the 6, 7, &amp; 8. Verſes. Theſe things being ſo
I ſhould think yet, with Submiſſion, that the Courſe of
the ſtory ſhould lie in the following Order, whereby all the
foremention'd inconvenience are avoided.</p>
            <p>I would then immediately after the 15th Chapter read
the 17th, (all but the 15th Verſe,) and the 6, 7, &amp; 8. Verſes
of the 18th Chapter, which make up a complete account
of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Expedition againſt the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> that Year, and
his Triumphant Return home. But whereas in the 8th
Verſe of that 18th Chapter it is ſaid, that <hi>Saul</hi> was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd,
becauſe the People aſcrib'd more unto <hi>David,</hi> than
unto the King, and ſays he, <hi>What can</hi> David <hi>have more, but the
Kingdom?</hi> Therefore in the next place, I would read
Verſe the 15th of the 17th Chapter—<hi>But David</hi> (obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
that <hi>Saul</hi> was angry, and himſelf in all likelihood, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated
of the Promiſe of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Daughter) <hi>went and return'd
from</hi> Saul <hi>to feed his Fathers Sheep at</hi> Bethlehem. Now God
among other Reaſons, to puniſh <hi>Saul</hi>'s breach of Promiſe
unto <hi>David,</hi> and to recompence <hi>David</hi> another way, ſent
<hi>Samuel</hi> to Anoint him <hi>Saul</hi>'s Succeſſor: I would in the
next place, then read the 16th Chapter intirely to the end.
The latter part whereof is an Account how <hi>David</hi> return'd
to Court, to Play upon his Harp and thereby to refreſh <hi>Saul,</hi>
when the Evil Spirit vexed him, as alſo how he was made
<hi>Saul</hi>'s Armour-Bearer. All this happen'd unto <hi>David,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
it was then well known, that <hi>David</hi> was a Skilful
Player on the Harp (we may ſuppoſe he had in the Camp
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30148:9"/>
frequently diverted the Souldiers with his Inſtrument) and
alſo that he was a Valiant Man, a Man of War, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
in ſuch matters, (for he had given proof of his Courage
and Conduct before in the War with the <hi>Philiſtines)</hi> When
<hi>David</hi> with his Harp, Chapter 16. 23. had refreſhed <hi>Saul</hi>
and the Evil Spirit was departed from him, I cannot but
think the King enter'd into ſome Diſcourſe with him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I would here go to the 18th Chapter and firſt Verſe, to
the end of the fifth—<hi>And it came to paſs when he had made an
end of ſpeaking unto</hi> Saul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—And <hi>David went out whither ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever</hi>
Saul <hi>ſent him, and behaved himſelf wiſely: And</hi> Saul <hi>ſet
him over the Men of War, and he was accepted in the ſight of all
the People and alſo in the ſight of</hi> Saul<hi>'s Servants.</hi> Laſtly,
hence I skip to the 9th Verſe—<hi>And Saul</hi> (being jealous of
<hi>David</hi> who was thus become popular and perhaps having
ſome ſecret Intelligence by this time, that he had been
Anointed to ſucceed in the Throne) <hi>Eyed</hi> David <hi>from that
day and forward.</hi> This Jealouſie brought again the Evil Spirit
upon <hi>Saul,</hi> ſo that in the very next the 10th Verſe 'tis ſaid
—<hi>And it came to paſs on the Morrow</hi> (of that day when <hi>Saul</hi>
began firſt to Eye <hi>David) that the Evil Spirit from God
came upon</hi> Saul, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſtory afterward is regular.</p>
            <p>It will (I foreſee well enough) be askt how all this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order
could happen in the ſacred Hiſtory? Whereunto I
Anſwer, that the matter of Fact ſeems to me ſo evident
both from the perplexity of the Narrative, as it lies at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
in our Bible, and from that perfect Agreement which
muſt be confeſt to be in the parts of the ſtory thus put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
that I reekon this not a ſufficient Objection. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
if I may be allow'd to account for this, as the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
do for other ſmaller Corruptions, I need not deſpair of
gueſſing at a probable way how this might come to paſs.</p>
            <p>Thus. The two greater Sections, which make up the
16th and 17th Chapters as they now ſtand in our Bibles,
might have been written upon two different Rolls or looſe
Parchments, &amp; ſo eaſily miſplac'd or miſtaken by the Copier,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30148:9"/>
taking up one for the other. The Reader afterwards ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving
<hi>David,</hi> who Chapter 16th was enter'd into <hi>Saul</hi>'s
Service, was now chap. 17. (no Body knows how, for no
account is given of it) at home again with his Father at
<hi>Bethlehem,</hi> noted in the Margin from a Neighbouring place
—<hi>But</hi> David <hi>went and returned from</hi> Saul <hi>to feed his Father's
Sheep at</hi> Bethlehem, which by degrees ſlipt from the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
into the Text here. Again, a Tranſcriber obſerving
there was no expreſs mention of any Diſcourſe between
<hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> except that in Chapter 17. 32. &amp; Verſe 58.
concluded, that the five firſt Verſes of the 18th Chap. ſhould
be plac'd immediately after the 17th Chapter, as they now
ſtand in our Bibles. Such kind of Accounts as theſe Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks
are wont to give of other miſtakes, why may not this
that I have now offer'd paſs as probable, at leaſt Poſſible. I
cannot admit of the Prolepſis, which the inſpir'd Pen-Men
of the Hiſtory would never have fallen into after ſuch a
groſs manner as renders the whole ſtory extremely confus'd,
and impoſſible to be clearly underſtood. In a word, the
Thread of the Hiſtory is ſo often broken, that it ſeem'd
neceſſary to reſtore the parts to their Natural Order, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
I do believe they were firſt written. But ſuppoſing the
Sacred Hiſtorian fell ſo often into the Prolepſis, yet it may be
be granted (I hope) that we have gain'd thus much by
this Attempt, that the genuine Order of time, when things
ſucceſſively happen'd, is here diſcover'd and render'd eaſy
to be underſtood, which I am Principally concern'd for.
But as for the explanations of ſeveral Difficulties in this
Hiſtory, which the Criticks in the Synopſis, who do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
upon the Prolepſis have furniſhed us with, I ſhall in the
laſt place ſhew, that they are weak, forc'd, and have no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability
at all in them.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid upon Chapter 17. 55, 58. that <hi>David</hi> was not
then ſufficiently known unto <hi>Saul,</hi> becauſe he frequently
went from Court home to feed his Father's Sheep: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the King enquir'd of him and of his Family.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:30148:10"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is incredible <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould ſuffer his Armour-Bearer
to retire ſo often to feed Sheep, or frequently diſpenſe with
<hi>his</hi> Abſence, who was to be conſtantly at hand to Play upon
the Harp, when ever the Evil Spirit came upon <hi>Saul.</hi>
Beſides, if <hi>David</hi> frequently went home, he frequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd
unto Court, and ſo was better known unto the King.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, <hi>Saul</hi> was taken up with the weighty Affairs of
the Kingdom, ſo that altho' he formerly knew <hi>David</hi> and
his Family, <hi>ch.</hi> 16. 18. yet he had forgot him, <hi>ch.</hi> 17. eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
being often troubled with the Evil Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Saul</hi> was not at that time troubled with the Evil
Spirit, it is manifeſt. If he had been often troubled with
it, yet he loſt not his Memory and Underſtanding thereby,
<hi>ch. 18. 10, 11. ch. 19. 9, 10, 11. David</hi> at the Combat with
<hi>Goliah</hi> was but Stripling twenty years old haply, for he was
but 30 at <hi>Saul</hi>'s Death, <hi>2 Sam.</hi> 5. 4. ſo that there could not
be ſufficient time between <hi>Saul</hi>'s making him his Armour-Bearer
and the Combat, for <hi>Saul</hi> to have forgot <hi>David.</hi>
In a word, Princes in their Conſulations about the Affairs
of State, are wont to confer with their Principal Officers
and Miniſters, of whom doubtleſs <hi>David</hi> the Armour-Bearer
was one, at leaſt had frequent Occaſions to attend
his Maſter, and laſtly, being often admitted into <hi>Saul</hi>'s
Preſence to Play upon the Harp, it is Morally impoſſible
<hi>Saul</hi> could in a little time forget him and his Father's Houſe.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid Princes are not wont to know their Servants,
eſpecially who have Merited at their Hands; therefore
<hi>Saul</hi> made himſelf ſtrange unto <hi>David, ch.</hi> 17. 55, 58. tho'
otherwiſe he could not chuſe but know him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Saul</hi> had no reaſon to diſſemble his knowledge of
<hi>David. David</hi> had oblig'd him by refreſhing him with his
Harp, and ſcaring away the Evil Spirit. But then <hi>Saul</hi> had
rewarded him with the Honourable Office of Armour-Bearer.
That which make Princes to forget, or to pretend
to forget their Subjects is, when they cannot, or will not
recompenſe them. But this was not the caſe. Again <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:30148:10"/>
had ſlain <hi>Goliah,</hi> and occaſion'd thereby the total defeat
and overthrow of the <hi>Philiſtines;</hi> this was a noble and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving
exploit. Right! But this was not the time, nor
was it to any purpoſe at preſent to hide his former know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
of <hi>David;</hi> For all <hi>David</hi>'s pretence now unto a further
reward of his Services, was his ſucceſsful Combate and
ſlaughter of the Giant, and preſervation of the Armies of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> thereby. As to the reward of this Action, it
matter'd not whether <hi>Saul</hi> had or had not been acquainted
with <hi>David</hi> formerly: Still the reward was due, though
<hi>Saul</hi> had never before ſeen or known him.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, <hi>David</hi>'s Face was changed and his Beard grown,
ſo that <hi>Saul</hi> knew him not again.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> How could <hi>David</hi>'s Beard be grown, who was as
yet but a Youth, a Stripling, and a Beardleſs Boy, <hi>ch.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, he appear'd now before <hi>Saul</hi> like a Shepherd,
and not in his Courtly Habit, ſo that <hi>Saul</hi> knew him not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis as eaſie to ſay, he appear'd at firſt, <hi>ch.</hi> 16. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the King in his Shepherd's Garb, which <hi>Saul</hi> might
eaſily know again.</p>
            <p>It is finally ſaid that <hi>Saul</hi> only enquir'd after the Lineage
of <hi>David;</hi> for he knew his Perſon well enough.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If <hi>Saul</hi> knew and remember'd <hi>David</hi>'s Perſon, he
could not have been ignorant of his Pedegree, Tribe and
Family, which were well known unto <hi>Saul</hi> when he made
him Armour-Bearer, <hi>ch.</hi> 16. 18, 19, 22.</p>
            <p>To conclude, many Incongruities in this ſtory are not
at all indeavour'd to be accounted for: Thoſe excuſes,
wherewith ſome of 'em are palliated, ſeem ſo trivial, weak
and ill grounded, that I am hereby farther and more firmly
convinc'd that the order of the ſtory has been ſome way or
other diſturb'd and ought ſome way or other to be rectify'd.
Whether I have contributed any thing thereunto, I leave
to the Judgment of other Men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:30148:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
There are two or three Obſervables more in the Order
of the ſtory, as 'tis found in our Bibles, which ought not to
be forgot. <hi>David</hi> was Anointed, and then advanc'd to be
<hi>Saul</hi>'s Armour-Bearer, <hi>ch.</hi> 16. God queſtionleſs deſigning
hereby to make way for his ſucceeding <hi>Saul</hi> in the Throne.
But <hi>David,</hi> tho' there had happen'd no diſguſt between him
and the King, return'd to keep his Father's
Sheep,<note place="margin">Ch. 17. 15.</note> and <hi>Jeſſe</hi> entertain'd him, which was
(as much as in them lay) to defeat the Purpoſe of God, and
expect another way than what God had appointed for his
attaining the Crown.<note place="margin">Ch. 17.</note> It might alſo be ask'd,
why did not the Armour-Bearer preſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
to his Maſter, make a tender of his Service according
to his Office? Whence was it, that he needed to be intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd
into the King's Preſence by ſome Courtier, and was
receiv'd as a mere Stranger. With what Face could <hi>Eliab</hi>
Challenge <hi>Saul</hi>'s Armour-Bearer with Pride and Naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of Heart for attending his Maſter in the War. In a
word, is it likely the King's Armour-Bearer ſhould appear
in the Field with his Shepherd's Habit, <hi>ch.</hi> 17. As yet
then he had been neither Anointed, nor taken into <hi>Saul</hi>'s Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
but was a mere Shepherd, and by Conſequence the
17th Chapter ought to be before the 16th, at leaſt is before
it in the Order of time, though the 16th by a bold Prolepſis
was put firſt by the Hiſtorian.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30148:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
